We're talking uh Japan and its influence
on the world economy. Let's start by
unpacking what has actually happened
here. So, the the recent event is the
intervention in the currency market by
Japan, uh but more notably by America,
too. The first uh uh such intervention
in about three decades. Uh Josh, could
you explain what's happened?
>> Yeah, so Scott Bessent, the US Treasury
Secretary, has basically bought an awful
lot of yen in order to to prop up its
value to to to try and stop it from
weakening. Um there are a couple of
unusual things about this. One is that
he used euros rather than dollars to buy
the yen. The other is the way we know
how much yen he bought, which there's
there's a lot about this administration
that we sometimes kind of criticize. One
thing I adore is the kind of high camp
theatricality, and it's it's just a very
theatrical way that we know we know that
um he's bought 5 to 10 billion dollars
worth of yen because he allowed a
photographer to take a picture of his
notepad at a at a cabinet meeting. Uh
and um the notepad says, "To do
um buy Japanese yen  JPY, in
case anybody missed it, that's the
that's the symbol for the Japanese yen,
5 to 10 billion dollars." That's the
only thing on the to-do list. Buy
Japanese yen, 5 to 10 billion dollars.
That's all. I mean, like you couldn't
get more theatrical unless you kind of
paid Patti LuPone to kind of belt it
from the rooftops.
>> And this has been a
ongoing battle for the Japanese uh
government, which uh as I said,
America's intervention was was was new,
but Japan has been defending uh its
currency for a while now. So, Ethan, in
the context of that, how much did this
intervention matter, do you think?
>> Yeah, it's a good question, Henry. And
uh I mean, I think it's worth saying
from the Japanese perspective, this is
an intensification of efforts that had
already been underway. Uh it came on the
back of a 73 billion dollar unilateral
intervention just by the Japanese
government in May and repeated efforts
by the finance minister and other
officials in Japan to jawbone the
markets to get the yen to cooperate. You
know, it used to be that a weak yen was
considered a a good thing for the
Japanese economy. It boosted exports.
Japan has a lot of very strong
multinationals where weak yen, you know,
improves their competitiveness abroad.
But now it's it's seen as as really a
problem for them. It it pushes up import
costs. It's seen as feeding into, you
know, above 2% inflation in Japan. It's
pinching,
you know, consumers and it's leading to
issues with overtourism which has become
a political issue for the government.
So, I you know, I think the politics
here are are are are shifting and you're
you're seeing that in the way that the
government is responding to yen
weakness.
Uh, you know, Takaichi-san, the prime
minister of Japan, is a long-time
skeptic of higher interest rates. Uh,
you know, she, before becoming prime
minister, said that
rate hikes were stupid. It's the word
she chose to use. And her tune has since
changed on on interest rate hikes as the
yen has become more of an issue. That's
why it matters in the Japanese context.
For America, I think it matters because
of the interactions between Japan and
the US Treasury market which I I know
we'll talk more about later in the show.
And then just more broadly for the
world, for global financial markets, it
matters because of the deep linkages
between what happens in Japan and the
rest of the world.
>> I think step one is saying
why is the yen so weak? And anyone who
uh, watched or read our coverage of our
Big Mac Index anniversary and and
refresh a few weeks back will remember
that Japan is one of the most
undervalued currencies according to the
Big Mac Index. So, that that that that
currency is weak. It's weak in defiance
of fundamentals and that's essentially
because
interest rates in Japan have been so low
for so long and that's what has made the
economy stand out. And of course, if
you're an investor, you want to hold a
currency where interest rates are
higher.
>> That's right. I mean, Japan for a long
time has had deflation as its primary
economic issue. Low growth, uh low
inflation, occasionally negative
inflation. And what that's meant is when
you have those sort of economic
conditions, you need lower interest
rates. So, from the from an investor
perspective, that makes it a very
attractive funding currency. In other
words, you'd like to borrow if there's
low interest rates in a country. That
lets you take that borrowed money from
Japan, finance it a low interest rate,
and invest it somewhere across borders,
and pick up uh the difference. So, that
that has been a long-standing feature of
global financial markets. The question
now is, you know, Japan used to have
negative 0.1% interest rates, but that's
changed. Inflation's back. It's been
above 2% for something like 4 years now,
and interest rates are rising. They're
now at about 1%. The expectation is that
the Bank of Japan, the central bank,
will hike again to 1.25% sometime later
this year. So, is that going to
destabilize this this this so-called
carry trade?
>> And essentially, the issue is that this
has happened on a massive scale, the
borrowing in in in yen to hold
higher-yielding assets overseas, not
least US Treasuries. And this chart
shows that Japan is indeed the biggest
holder of US
US Treasuries. So, this is happening on
a on a large scale, right, Josh?
>> Right, exactly. And that's why Scott
Bessent does need to be worried about
Japan. They are such a big holder of
Treasuries. If something goes wrong,
they start to dump their Treasury
holdings, that would send US borrowing
costs up. But, it's not just that.
Traders call Japan the world's ATM. As
Ethan said, it's so it's such a
low-yielding currency that you can
easily borrow in it and buy other
assets. And that goes well beyond
Treasuries, right? That goes to Japanese
stocks, that goes to other Asian stocks,
that even goes to US tech stocks. So, if
we start to see this carry trade unwind,
if we start to see, you know, interest
rates go up, it becomes more expensive
to borrow in the yen,
um it's not so attractive to use that as
your funding currency anymore. You can
see sell-offs across the world. And
that's why we're asking, you know, can
Japan break the financial system because
it's such an important part of it.
>> Okay, so that brings us on to the big
question. Will Japan bring down the
global financial system?
>> Well, if it doesn't manage the dream
scenario where it just gradually kind of
unwinds, it's it it it it's big carry
trade, it it it could do. And the the
worrying thing is that
we have a financial system that already
has points of fragility that have
nothing to do with Japan. We have talked
to death about how
how high stock market valuations are,
how vulnerable they are to a crash. Two
summers ago, you know, when when part of
the carry trade was unwinding, you know,
but this is this is tech stocks
um falling from a very high level. They
have much further to fall. They're much
more highly valued now than they were
two summers ago. So, that's a point of
vulnerability. You have this kind of
inward turn already happening within
countries, you know, uh cross-border
capital flows reorienting themselves
along geopolitical lines. This could be
one of those kind of catalysts that that
that really accelerates that. And you
can't really predict if you have kind of
this inward turn, you can't really
predict what shape the financial system
takes after that. So, yes, I worry that
it could bring down the the financial
system. I do hold out hope though
that we just get repeated episodes like
over the past few weeks, this big point
of vulnerability, the um
the the the
essentially the Japanese government's
consolidated position winds down and
down and down, and then eventually we
don't have it anymore, and that's maybe
one problem less for for the world to
worry about.
>> Let me give the more optimistic take
here, which is that I I think even
though the position is scary, I think
governments are pretty good at crisis
fighting generally speaking and I think
Japan has a lot of levers to pull if
something you know started to turn
pear-shaped quite quickly. I mean the
asset side of the balance sheet Henry is
one of those levers. A lot of those
assets you know could be unwound could
be monetized
if need be. There is a really
significant stock of foreign reserves to
defend the currency if they needed to.
The August 2024 episode though it
created this volatility nothing really
broke. This was not a GFC or or a
pandemic style scenario. It was a
warning signal but nothing you know
absolutely dire. And so I I think with
the levers the government has to pull
the funds available to its disposal and
coordination with you know its friends
in America I think a crisis situation
probably could be averted but you know
that's probably what people would have
said in the 80s before that the the
gigantic bubble burst in Japan. But I I
I think I have faith that governments
tend to be good at crisis fighting even
if they're not always good at making
good decisions when things aren't in
crisis.